One day in 1819,
ذات يوم في عام 1819
3,000 miles off the coast of Chile,
و على بعد 3000 ميلاً من ساحل تشيلى
in one of the most remote regions of the Pacific Ocean,
في إحدى المناطق النائية في المحيط الهادئ
20 American sailors watched their ship flood with seawater.
شهد 20 بحارًا أميركيًا غرق سفينتهم في البحر
They'd been struck by a sperm whale, which had ripped
هاجمهم حوت العنبر
a catastrophic hole in the ship's hull.
و أحدث ثقبًا هائلاً في هيكل السفينة
As their ship began to sink beneath the swells,
ولما بدأت سفينتهم في الغرق وسط الأمواج العالية
the men huddled together in three small whaleboats.
تجمع الرجال في ثلاثة قوارب نجاة صغيرة
These men were 10,000 miles from home,
كان هؤلاء الرجال على بعد عشرة آلاف ميل من وطنهم
more than 1,000 miles from the nearest scrap of land.
وأكثر من ألف ميل من أقرب بقعة على اليابسة
In their small boats, they carried only
كلّ ما حملوه على قواربهم الصغيرة
rudimentary navigational equipment
لم يتعدَّ آلةً ملاحيّة بدائيّة
and limited supplies of food and water.
وكميات محددودة من الماء والطعام.
These were the men of the whaleship Essex,
هؤلاء هم رجال سفينة إسكس،
whose story would later inspire parts of "Moby Dick."
والتي ألهمت قصتهم أجزاء من قصة "موبي ديك".
Even in today's world, their situation would be really dire,
حتي لو حدث ذلك في يومنا هذا، لسيكون موقفهم خطير أيضًا.
but think about how much worse it would have been then.
تخيّلوا إذًا كم كان الأمر سيئًا في ذلك الزمان
No one on land had any idea that anything had gone wrong.
فلا أحد على اليابسة علم بما حلّ بهم
No search party was coming to look for these men.
ولم تخرج فِرَقُ للبحث عن هؤلاء الرجال.
So most of us have never experienced a situation
إذًا، معظما لم يمرّ بتجربةً مماثلة
as frightening as the one in which these sailors found themselves,
ومخيفةٍ إلى هذا الحدّ الذي وجد هؤلاء البحّارة أنفسهم فيه
but we all know what it's like to be afraid.
ولكننا جميعًا نعلم ماذا يعني أن نخاف
We know how fear feels,
نعلم كيف يكون الشعور بالخوف
but I'm not sure we spend enough time thinking about
ولكني أشك في أننا نقضي الوقت الكافي
what our fears mean.
للتقكير في معنى مخاوفنا
As we grow up, we're often encouraged to think of fear
وبينما نكبر، نُشجـَّعُ على النظر إلى الخوف كعلامة للضعف
as a weakness, just another childish thing to discard
وعلى أنّه مجرد شعور طفولي آخر علينا التخلص منه
like baby teeth or roller skates.
كما تخلصنا من الأسنان اللبنية وألواح التزلق.
And I think it's no accident that we think this way.
وأعتقد أن تفكيرنا بهذ الطريقة ليس مجرد صدفة.
Neuroscientists have actually shown that human beings
فعلماء الأعصاب أظهروا أن البشر
are hard-wired to be optimists.
متفائلون فطريًّا
So maybe that's why we think of fear, sometimes,
لذا ربما لهذا الأمر نفكّر أحيانًا في الخوف
as a danger in and of itself.
على أنّه خطرٌ في حدّ ذاته
"Don't worry," we like to say to one another. "Don't panic."
دائمًا ما نقول لبعضنا البعض "لا تقلق"، "لا تخف"
In English, fear is something we conquer.
باللغة الإنجليزية، الخوف هو شيءٌ نقهره
It's something we fight. It's something we overcome.
شيءٌ نحاربه، شيءٌ نتغلّبُ عليه
But what if we looked at fear in a fresh way?
ولكن ماذا لو نظرنا إلى الخوف نظرة جديدة؟
What if we thought of fear as an amazing act of the imagination,
ماذا لو اعتبرناه دربًا من دروب الخيال
something that can be as profound and insightful
شيئًا عميقًا وذا معنىً
as storytelling itself?
كرواية القصص؟
It's easiest to see this link between fear and the imagination
من الأسهل رؤية العلاقة بين الخوف والخيال
in young children, whose fears are often extraordinarily vivid.
في الأطفال الذين تكون مخاوفهم -عادةً- جليّة بصورةٍ غير عاديّة
When I was a child, I lived in California,
عندما كنتُ صغيرة، عشتُ في كاليفورنيا
which is, you know, mostly a very nice place to live,
والتي تعتبر-كما تعرفون- مكانًا جميلاً جدًا للعيش فيه
but for me as a child, California could also be a little scary.
ولكن بالنسبة لطفلة، كانت كاليفورنيا أحيانًا مكانًا يخيفني قليلاً
I remember how frightening it was to see the chandelier
أذكرُ كم كنتُ أخاف عند رؤية الثريّا
that hung above our dining table swing back and forth
المعلق فوق طاولتنا كلما تحرك ذهابًا وإيابًا
during every minor earthquake,
اثناء حدوث أيّ زلزال بسيط
and I sometimes couldn't sleep at night, terrified
وأحيانًا كنت لا أنام في الليل بسبب فزعي
that the Big One might strike while we were sleeping.
من أن يضرب" الزلزال الكبير" بيتنا ونحن نائمون
And what we say about kids who have fears like that
ونحن نعتبر الاطفال الذين لديهم مثل هذه المخاوف
is that they have a vivid imagination.
أنّ لديهم خيالاً حيًّا
But at a certain point, most of us learn
واكن في مرحلة ما،يتعلم معظمنا
to leave these kinds of visions behind and grow up.
هجر هذه الخيالات والنضج.
We learn that there are no monsters hiding under the bed,
ونكتشف لأنه لا توجد عفاريت أسفل مضاجعنا
and not every earthquake brings buildings down.
ولا تهدم جميع الزلازل المباني
But maybe it's no coincidence that some of our most creative minds
ولكن ربما ليس مصادفة أنّ بعض عقولنا الخلاّقة
fail to leave these kinds of fears behind as adults.
تفشل في ترك مثل هذه المخاوف عند الكبر
The same incredible imaginations that produced "The Origin of Species,"
الخيال الحادّ نفسه الذي أنتج "أصل الأنواع"
"Jane Eyre" and "The Remembrance of Things Past,"
و"جين آير" و"ذكرى الأشياء السابقة"
also generated intense worries that haunted the adult lives
ولّدت أيضًا قلقًا شديدًا طارد حياة البالغين
of Charles Darwin, Charlotte BrontÍ and Marcel Proust.
من أمثال تشارلز داروين، وشارلوت برونتيومارسيل بروست
So the question is, what can the rest of us learn about fear
إذًا يكمن السؤال في:ماذا يمكن لنا نحن البقيّة أن نتعلّم عن الخوف؟
from visionaries and young children?
من الرؤى والأطفال الصغار؟
Well let's return to the year 1819 for a moment,
حسنًا، دعونا نعود إلى العام 1819 للحظة
to the situation facing the crew of the whaleship Essex.
للوضع الذي واجهه طاقم سفينة إيسيكس
Let's take a look at the fears that their imaginations
فلنلقِ نظرة إلى مخاوفهم التي ولّدتها خيالاتهم
were generating as they drifted in the middle of the Pacific.
بينما جُرفوا في مياه المحيط الهادئ
Twenty-four hours had now passed since the capsizing of the ship.
مرت 24 ساعة الآن منذ انقلاب السفينة
The time had come for the men to make a plan,
وحان الوقت ليضع الرجال خطّة
but they had very few options.
إلاّ إنّ خياراتهم كانت قليلة جدًّا
In his fascinating account of the disaster,
في تقريره المُبهِر عن الكارثة
Nathaniel Philbrick wrote that these men were just about
كتب ناثانيل فيلبريك أنّ
as far from land as it was possible to be anywhere on Earth.
أبعد من اليابسة كما لو كانت مستحيلة بأن تكون على الأرض
The men knew that the nearest islands they could reach
الرجال عرفوا بأن أقرب الجزر التي يستطيعون الوصول اليها
were the Marquesas Islands, 1,200 miles away.
كانت جزر الماركوسوس, على بعد 1200 ميل
But they'd heard some frightening rumors.
ولكنهم سمعوا شائعات مخيفة
They'd been told that these islands,
قيل لهم بأن هذه الجزر
and several others nearby, were populated by cannibals.
و الكثير من الجزر المحيطة تسكنها أكلة لحوم البشر
So the men pictured coming ashore only to be murdered
لذلك تخيل الرجال مقتلهم بمجرد وصولوهم الى الى الشاطي
and eaten for dinner.
وتحضيرهم كوجبة عشاء
Another possible destination was Hawaii,
كانت هاواي وجهة اأخرى
but given the season, the captain was afraid
نظراً لحلول الموسم, كان الكابتن متخوفاً
they'd be struck by severe storms.
من أن تصيبهم العواصف الشديدة
Now the last option was the longest, and the most difficult:
الان, الحل الأخير هو الأطول و الأكثر صعوبة
to sail 1,500 miles due south in hopes of reaching
الأبحار 1500 ميل جنوباً في أميل البحث
a certain band of winds that could eventually
عن بعض الأمواج التي قد اخيراً
push them toward the coast of South America.
تدفع بهم الى سواحل الجنوب الأمريكي
But they knew that the sheer length of this journey
ولكن كانوا يعرفوا طول هذه الرحلة
would stretch their supplies of food and water.
قد ينزف مخزوناتهم من الطعام والماء
To be eaten by cannibals, to be battered by storms,
ليؤكلوا بواسطة أكلي لحوم البشر, وليضربوا بالعواصف
to starve to death before reaching land.
و ليجُعوا حتى الموت قبل الوصول إلى البر
These were the fears that danced in the imaginations of these poor men,
هذه هي المخاوف التي كانت ترقص في مخيلات هولاء الرجال الضعفاء
and as it turned out, the fear they chose to listen to
و كما اتضح فما بعد, أن الخوف الذي اختاروا ان ينصتوا له
would govern whether they lived or died.
أصبح من يحكم إما أن يعيشوا او يموتوا
Now we might just as easily call these fears by a different name.
ألان بإستطاعتنا بكل سهولة أن نسمي هذه المخاوف بأسماء مختلفة
What if instead of calling them fears,
ولكن ماذا لو بدلاً من نسميها مخاوف
we called them stories?
نسميها قصص؟
Because that's really what fear is, if you think about it.
لان فعلاً هذا هوا الخوف , اذا فكرت في الموضوع
It's a kind of unintentional storytelling
هو عبارة عن رواية القصص الغير مقصود
that we are all born knowing how to do.
جمعينا ولدنا ونحن نعلم ماذا نفعل
And fears and storytelling have the same components.
والخوف و رواية القصص يحتون على المكونات ذاتها
They have the same architecture.
لديهم البنية ذاتها
Like all stories, fears have characters.
مثل كل القصص, الخوف له شخصيات
In our fears, the characters are us.
في مخاوفنا, الشخصيات هي نحن
Fears also have plots. They have beginnings and middles and ends.
الخوف فيه حبكة درامية. له بدايات, و منتصفات و نهايات
You board the plane. The plane takes off. The engine fails.
أنت من يحلق بالطائرة.
Our fears also tend to contain imagery that can be
مخاوفنا أيضا تميل إلى أنت تحتوي مجازات والتي قد تكون
every bit as vivid as what you might find in the pages of a novel.
واضحة مثل ما قد تجده في صفحات رواية
Picture a cannibal, human teeth
تصور أكل للحوم البشر, أسنان بشر
sinking into human skin,
في جلد بشر
human flesh roasting over a fire.
لحم بشري يحمص على النار
Fears also have suspense.
المخاوف لها تسلسل
If I've done my job as a storyteller today,
إذا أستطعت اليوم بأن أقوم بدوري كراوية للقصص
you should be wondering what happened
يجب عليك أن تكون متعجب مما حدث
to the men of the whaleship Essex.
لرجال حيتان إيسكس
Our fears provoke in us a very similar form of suspense.
مخاوفنا تحرض فينا تسلسل مشابه
Just like all great stories, our fears focus our attention
مثل جميع القصص العظيمة, مخاوفتا تركز إنتباهنا
on a question that is as important in life as it is in literature:
على سؤال مهم في حياتنا كأهميته في الأدب
What will happen next?
ماذا سوف يحدث بعد؟
In other words, our fears make us think about the future.
وبعبارة أخرى, مخاوفنا تجعلنا نفكر في مستقبلنا
And humans, by the way, are the only creatures capable
وبالمناسبة, البشر هم المخلوقات الوحيدة القادرة
of thinking about the future in this way,
على التفكير في المستقبل بهذه الطريقة
of projecting ourselves forward in time,
من تصور أنفسنا في نقطة متقدمة من الوقت
and this mental time travel is just one more thing
و هذه الرحلة الذهنية تعتبر نشيء أخر
that fears have in common with storytelling.
تتشارك فيها مخاوفنا مع رواية القصة
As a writer, I can tell you that a big part of writing fiction
ككاتب, أستطيع إخباركم بأنها جزء كبير من الكتابة الرواية
is learning to predict how one event in a story
عبارة عن تعلم التنبؤ بكيف يمكن لحدث في القصة
will affect all the other events,
التأثير على جميع الأحداث الاخرى
and fear works in that same way.
الخوف يعمل بنفس الطريقة
In fear, just like in fiction, one thing always leads to another.
مثل ما هو الحال في الرواية, في الخوف شيء واحد يقود دائما الأخر
When I was writing my first novel, "The Age Of Miracles,"
عندما كنت رواية الاولى " The age of Miracles""زمن المعجزات"
I spent months trying to figure out what would happen
قضيت شهوراً في محاولة فهم ما قد يحدث
if the rotation of the Earth suddenly began to slow down.
إذا أبتدءت حركة دوران الكرة بالبطء تدريجياً
What would happen to our days? What would happen to our crops?
ماذا قد يحدث لأيامنا؟ ماذا سوف قد يحدث لمحاصيلنا؟
What would happen to our minds?
ماذا قد يحدث لعقولنا؟
And then it was only later that I realized how very similar
لاحقأ, ادركت كيف هي مشابة
these questions were to the ones I used to ask myself
تلك الأسئلة لتلك التي كنت أسئلها لنفسي
as a child frightened in the night.
مثل طفلاً خائفاً في الليل
If an earthquake strikes tonight, I used to worry,
كنت أقلق إذا ضربت هزة أرضية الليلة
what will happen to our house? What will happen to my family?
ماذا سوف يحدث لمنزلنا؟ ماذا سوف يحدث لعائلتي؟
And the answer to those questions always took the form of a story.
كانت إجابة هذة الأسئلة عادةً ما تأخذ شكل قصة
So if we think of our fears as more than just fears
لذلك لو فكرنا في مخاوفنا على أنها ليست مجرد مخاوف
but as stories, we should think of ourselves
ولكن قصص, يجب علينا التفكر في أنفسنا
as the authors of those stories.
كمؤلفين لتلك القصص
But just as importantly, we need to think of ourselves
ولكن لنفس القدر من الأهمية، يتعين علينا أن نفكر في أنفسنا
as the readers of our fears, and how we choose
كقراء لهذه المخاوف و كيف
to read our fears can have a profound effect on our lives.
أن نقرأ مخاوفنا يمكن أن يكون له تأثير عميق على حياتنا
Now, some of us naturally read our fears more closely than others.
الآن, منا من يقرأ, مخاوفنا عن كثب أكثر من البعض الأخر
I read about a study recently of successful entrepreneurs,
قرأت موخراً دراسة عن رجال أعمال ناجحين
and the author found that these people shared a habit
وجد الكاتب أن هولاء الناس يشتركون في صفة
that he called "productive paranoia," which meant that
تدعى "جنون الإرتياب الإنتاجي" والتي تعني
these people, instead of dismissing their fears,
أن هؤلاء الناس يقرأون و يدرسون مخاوفهم بدلاً من تجاهلها
these people read them closely, they studied them,
هؤلاء الناس قراءتها عن كثب، وأنها تدرس لهم،
and then they translated that fear into preparation and action.
و يترجمون هذا الخوف إلى تحضير و فعل
So that way, if their worst fears came true,
وبهذه الطريقة, إذا أسواء مخاوفهم أصبحت حقيقة
their businesses were ready.
تجارتهم تكون جاهزة
And sometimes, of course, our worst fears do come true.
طبعاً في بعض الأوقات مخاوفنا تتحقق
That's one of the things that is so extraordinary about fear.
هذا أمر من الأمور التي تعتير غير إعتيادية عن الخوف
Once in a while, our fears can predict the future.
مابين الحين والاخرى, تستطيع مخاوفنا التنبوء بالمستقبل
But we can't possibly prepare for all of the fears
ولكن ليس من المحتمل الإستعداد لكل مخاوفنا
that our imaginations concoct.
تلك هي خيالتنا الملفقة.
So how can we tell the difference between
فكيف يمكننا معرفة الفرق بين
the fears worth listening to and all the others?
المخاوف تستحق الاستماع ، وجميع الآخرين؟
I think the end of the story of the whaleship Essex
وأعتقد أن نهاية القصة ويلشيب إسكس
offers an illuminating, if tragic, example.
ويقدم الإنارة، إذا كانت مأساوية، مثال.
After much deliberation, the men finally made a decision.
وبعد الكثير من المداولات، أدلى الرجال أخيرا قرارا.
Terrified of cannibals, they decided to forgo the closest islands
قرروا التخلي عن الجزر الأقرب بسبب خوفهم من أكلة لحوم البشر،
and instead embarked on the longer
وبدلاً من ذلك سلك الطريق الأطول
and much more difficult route to South America.
وأصعب بكثير من الطريق إلى أمريكا الجنوبية.
After more than two months at sea, the men ran out of food
بعد أكثر من شهرين في البحر، نفد الرجال من الغذاء
as they knew they might,
كما أنهم يعرفون أنهم قد،
and they were still quite far from land.
وأنها كانت لا تزال بعيدة عن الأرض.
When the last of the survivors were finally picked up
عندما آخر الناجين تم أخيرا التقطت
by two passing ships, less than half of the men were left alive,
بمرور سفينتين، أقل من نصف الرجال تركت على قيد الحياة،
and some of them had resorted to their own form of cannibalism.
والبعض منهم قد لجأت إلى النموذج الخاصة بهم من أكل لحوم البشر.
Herman Melville, who used this story as research for "Moby Dick,"
هيرمان ميلفيل، الذين استخدموا هذه القصة كالبحث عن "موبي ديك"،
wrote years later, and from dry land, quote,
كتب في سنوات لاحقة، ومن الأراضي الجافة، اقتباس،
"All the sufferings of these miserable men of the Essex
"جميع معاناة هؤلاء الرجال بائسة اسيكس
might in all human probability have been avoided
ربما في جميع الاحتمالات البشرية قد تم تجنب
had they, immediately after leaving the wreck,
وقد كانوا، فورا بعد ترك الحطام،
steered straight for Tahiti.
قاد مباشرة لتاهيتي.
But," as Melville put it, "they dreaded cannibals."
ولكن، "كما قال ميلفيل،" أنهم أكلة لحوم البشر المرتاعين".
So the question is, why did these men dread cannibals
السؤال هو، لماذا هؤلاء الرجال الفزّع أكلة لحوم البشر
so much more than the extreme likelihood of starvation?
الأكثر أرجحية من احتمال التضور جوعا ؟
Why were they swayed by one story
لماذا كانت هي أن تجرفنا قصة واحدة
so much more than the other?
أكثر من ذلك بكثير من الآخر؟
Looked at from this angle,
ينظر إليها من هذه الزاوية،
theirs becomes a story about reading.
ويصبح لهم قصة عن القراءة.
The novelist Vladimir Nabokov said that the best reader
وقال الروائي فلاديمير نابوكوف أن القارئ أفضل
has a combination of two very different temperaments,
مزيج من اثنين من الامزجة مختلفة جداً،
the artistic and the scientific.
الفني والعلمي.
A good reader has an artist's passion,
قارئ جيد لديه شغف فنان،
a willingness to get caught up in the story,
رغبة في الحصول على المحاصرين في القصة،
but just as importantly, the readers also needs
ولكن يحتاج إلى نفس القدر من الأهمية، القراء أيضا
the coolness of judgment of a scientist,
رباطة جأش الحكم لأحد العلماء،
which acts to temper and complicate
الأفعال التي للمزاج وتعقد
the reader's intuitive reactions to the story.
ردود فعل القارئ البديهية للقصة.
As we've seen, the men of the Essex had no trouble with the artistic part.
كما شاهدنا،لم يكن لرجال اسيكس مشكلة مع الجزء الفني.
They dreamed up a variety of horrifying scenarios.
أنها حلمت مجموعة متنوعة من سيناريوهات مرعبة.
The problem was that they listened to the wrong story.
والمشكلة أن استمعوا إلى قصة خاطئة.
Of all the narratives their fears wrote,
وكتب جميع السرود مخاوفهم،
they responded only to the most lurid, the most vivid,
أنهم ورد فقط لمعظم متوهج، الأكثر وضوحاً،
the one that was easiest for their imaginations to picture:
تلك التي كان أسهل لما خيال للصورة:
cannibals.
أكلة لحوم البشر.
But perhaps if they'd been able to read their fears
ولكن ربما إذا تمكنت من قراءة مخاوفهم
more like a scientist, with more coolness of judgment,
أكثر مثل عالم، مع مزيد من رباطة جأش من الحكم،
they would have listened instead to the less violent
سيكون قد استمع بدلاً من ذلك إلى أقل عنفاً
but the more likely tale, the story of starvation,
ولكن حكاية أكثر احتمالاً، وقصة المجاعة،
and headed for Tahiti, just as Melville's sad commentary suggests.
وتوجهت لتاهيتي، مثلما ميلفيل لحزين التعليق تقترح.
And maybe if we all tried to read our fears,
وربما لو حاولنا قراءة مخاوفنا،
we too would be less often swayed
نحن أيضا, قد نكون أقل تخبطا بكثير
by the most salacious among them.
بسبب الجانب الأكثر رهبة من بين تلك المخاوف.
Maybe then we'd spend less time worrying about
ربما ثم سننفق وقتا أقل في القلق بشأن
serial killers and plane crashes,
القتلة المسجلين و حوادث الطائرات،
and more time concerned with the subtler
و نعطي وقتا أكبر للإهتمام بأمور أقل
and slower disasters we face:
وأبطأ من الكوارث التي نواجهها:
the silent buildup of plaque in our arteries,
صمت تراكم البلاك في الشرايين داخل أجسامنا،
the gradual changes in our climate.
تغييرات تدريجية في مناخنا.
Just as the most nuanced stories in literature are often the richest,
فقط كالقصص الأكثر دقة في الأدب كثيرا ما أغنى،
so too might our subtlest fears be the truest.
حتى جداً يمكن أن مخاوفنا الألطف أصدق.
Read in the right way, our fears are an amazing gift
قراءة في الطريق الصحيح، مخاوفنا هدية مذهلة
of the imagination, a kind of everyday clairvoyance,
من الخيال، نوع من استبصار اليومية،
a way of glimpsing what might be the future
وسيلة لاستشراف ما قد يكون المستقبل
when there's still time to influence how that future will play out.
عندما لا يزال هناك وقت للتأثير على كيفية أن المستقبل سوف يمر.
Properly read, our fears can offer us something as precious
قراءة مخاوفنا بشكل صحيح، يمكن أن تقدم لنا شيئا ثمينا
as our favorite works of literature:
كما تقول الأعمال الأدبية المفضلة:
a little wisdom, a bit of insight
قليل من الحكمة، قليلاً من البصيرة
and a version of that most elusive thing --
ونسخة من ذلك الشيء الأكثر مراوغة-
the truth.
الحقيقة.
Thank you. (Applause)
شكرا. (تصفيق)